I like to build stuff.
أحب أن أبني الأشياء.
I've always liked to build stuff.
لطالما أحببت بناء الأشياء.
My team at Biosense,
فريقي في بيوسانس،
a startup I co-founded with my doctor and engineer friends,
هو فريق مقاولة شاركت في تأسيسها مع أصدقاء مهندسين ودكاترة،
has built a technology called ToucHB,
قد بنت تكنولوجيا تدعى ToucHB،
which can do blood testing of hemoglobin
والتي يمكنها القيام بفحص دم للهيموغلوبين
without pricks, without needles.
من دون غرزات ومن دون إبر.
I believe
أعتقد
this is going to democratize health care.
أن هذا سيقوم بدمقرطة الرعاية الصحية.
They're two big words, I don't know what they mean.
هما كلمتان كبيرتان، لا أدري ما تعنيه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In fact, in 2009, I was even more clueless.
في الواقع، سنة 2009، كنت أكثر جهلا حتى.
I had absolutely no idea
لم تكن لدي أدنى فكرة
what was going to happen next.
عما سيحدث لاحقا.
I was, in fact, busy trying to finish off my Ph.D.,
كنت في الواقع مشغولا أحاول إنهاء شهادة الدكتوراه،
which was in a completely unrelated area
والتي كانت في مجال مختلف تماما
of how people interact, contributors interact,
حول كيف يتفاعل الناس، كيف يتفاعل المساهمون،
how articles are formed in Wikipedia --
كيف تتشكل المقالات في ويكيبيديا --
trying to figure out how quality emerges from the system.
محاولا فهم كيف تنبثق الجودة من النظام.
I was also building something
كنت كذلك أبني شيئا
called the Copenhagen Wheel,
يدعى عجلة كوبنهاغن،
which is just a really beautiful, beautiful electric bike
وهي دراجة كهربائية في غاية الجمال
at a lab at MIT called SENSEable City Lab.
في مختبر في MIT يدعى مختبر SENSEable City.
I was lucky enough that I visited Mumbai, my house,
كنت محظوظا لما يكفي أن أزور مومباي، منزلي،
back for a vacation.
في عطلة.
So at that time
لذا في ذلك الوقت
I was planning a road trip.
كنت أخطط لرحلة طرقية.
I visited a place called Parol
زرت مكانا يدعى بارول
about two hours north of Mumbai.
يبعد بحوالي الساعتين شمال مومباي.
This is a place where my friend, Abhishek Sen was interning.
هذا مكان حيث كان صديقي ابهيشيك سين يتلقى تدريبه.
He's a doctor there.
إنه دكتور هنا.
And that's his actual photograph.
وتلك صورته الحقيقية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So Abhishek actually made me wait.
حسنا ابهيشيك جعلني أنتظر.
He was out there in Parol delivering a baby.
كان خارجا في بارول لتوليد طفل.
I was waiting, and when he did emerge,
كنت أنتظر، وحين ظهر،
he was ashen-faced.
كان شاحب الوجه.
He told me that there had been two deaths;
أخبرني أنه وقعت حالتا وفاة؛
the mother and child both had died.
الأم والطفل كلاهما قد مات.
The reason, he told me,
والسبب كما أخبرني
was something called post partum hemorrhage.
هو شيء يدعى نزيف ما بعد الولادة.
He explained this meant severe internal bleeding.
وقد شرح لي أن هذا يعني نزيفا داخليا حادا.
What was really shocking for me
والذي كان بالفعل صدمة لي
was that he said that this is entirely due
لقد قال أن هذا راجع بشكل كامل
to undiagnosed anemia.
لفقر الدم الغير مشخص.
Now anemia -- I'm an engineer, but even I knew --
الآن فقر الدم -- أنا مهندس، لكن حتى أنا أعرف ماهيته --
that anemia is something which is not supposed to be fatal.
إن فقر الدم هو شيء لا يفترض أن يكون قاتلا.
It is something which probably the cure is known.
إنه أمر معروف علاجه على الأرجح.
I mean, folic acid, iron tablets --
أقصد، بإستخدام حمض الفوليك، حبوب الحديد --
very cheap, affordable cures exist
والتي هي رخيصة جدا، و أسعار علاجه معقولة جداً
to control anemia.
وبالإمكان التحكم في فقر الدم.
So why was this woman dying?
حسنا لماذا كانت هذه المرأة تموت؟
It was completely preventable.
كان من الممكن تماما الوقاية من ذلك.
Five minutes away from there,
على بعد خمس دقائق من هناك،
I had the center, the medical center,
كان لي مركز، المركز الصحي،
which was distributing subsidized iron tablets.
والذي كان يوزع أقراص الحديد المدعمة.
So the whole nature of this thing completely shocked me.
وبالتالي فالطبيعة الكلية لهذا الأمر قد صدمتني تماما.
And I knew that there had to be a way to prevent this.
وعلمت أنه من الضروري أن تكون هناك وسيلة لمنع ذلك.
My mom is a pediatrician, and I asked her.
أمي طبيبة أطفال، حدثتها لاحقا.
She told me that this is how you would typically test for anemia.
أخبرتني أن هذه هي الطريقة التي تفحص من خلالها فقر الدم عادة.
Take a blood sample
تأخذ عينة دم
and run it through a machine called a Coulter counter.
وتمررها خلال آلة تدعى عداد كولتر.
This is a $10,000 machine which was available in Mumbai.
وهذه آلة بقيمة 10,000 دولار والتي كانت متوفرة في مومباي.
It's also available here or in any part, I guess,
أظنها متوفرة كذلك هنا أو في أي جزء
in Europe and most cities in the world.
من أوروبا وفي معظم مدن العالم.
But this is not available in Parol.
لكن هذه غير متوفرة في بارول.
Also, that woman who was operating the machine, the technician,
كذلك تلك المرأة التي كانت تشغل الآلة، التقنية،
is not available in Parol.
ليست متوفرة في بارول.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now this struck me as --
الآن هذا قد صدمني --
I love to fix things. I wanted to fix this.
لأنني أحب إصلاح الأشياء. أردت إصلاح هذا.
I got a friend of mine, an engineer, and three other doctors --
لدي صديق مهندس، وثلاثة دكاترة آخرين --
Abhishek joined the team --
أبهيشك انضم للفريق --
and we wanted to solve this problem.
وأردنا أن نحل هذا المشكل.
By the time I step down from here
في الوقت الذي أكون قد نزلت من هنا
there will be 10 people who have lost their lives
سيكون 10 أشخاص قد فقدوا حياتهم
through a completely, completely preventable problem.
بسبب مشكلة يمكن الوقاية منها بشكل كامل.
Now let me take you back to Parol.
الآن دعوني أعود بكم إلى بارول.
You saw the woman there, the nurse.
قد رأيتم المرأة هناك، الممرضة.
In India this is called an ASHA worker.
في الهند تسمى عاملة آشا.
It's essentially a village health worker, a matron.
إنها في الأساس عاملة صحية قروية ، رئيسة ممرضات.
She is really the center of the health care system.
إنها بالفعل مركز نظام رعاية صحية كامل.
Public health care runs on the ASHA worker,
الرعاية الصحية العامة تعتمد على عامل آشا،
not the doctor.
ليس الطبيب.
Now we knew we had to design something
الآن عرفنا أنه علينا تصميم شيء
which she could use.
يمكنها استخدامه.
We knew it had to be these three things that the machine had to have.
عرفنا أنه يجب أن تتوفر الآلة على هذه الأشياء الثلاثة.
We knew it had to be something
عرفنا أنه يجب أن يكون شيء
which had no needles, no pricking,
لا يحتوي على إبر، ولا وخز
so it would have adoption, it would not have medical waste,
وبالتالي لن تترتب عنه نفايات طبية،
all those problems.
كل تلك المشاكل.
It had to be simple enough for that woman ASHA worker to use.
ويجب أن يكون بسيطا بما فيه الكفاية لتستخدمه تلك المرأة، عاملة آشا.
And thirdly, it had to be something which she could carry in her kit.
وثالثا، وجب أ، يكون شيء يمكن أن تحمله في عدتها.
She goes village to village doing screenings.
تذهب من قرية لقرية للقيام بالفحوصات.
We thought we could build it,
ظننا أنه بإمكاننا بناؤه،
so we built it.
وبالتالي بنيناه.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But, but it didn't work.
لكن، لكنه لم يشتغل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we built it again.
وبالتالي بنيناه مجددا.
And we did this 32 times.
وقمنا بذلك 32 مرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I'm very excited to tell you
لكنني متحمسة جدا لإخباركم
that last year
أنه في السنة الماضية
we did build it -- it works.
قمنا بالفعل ببناءه -- إنه يشتغل.
And I have it here in my purse.
إنه موجود لدي هنا في محفظتي.
So this is a machine
إذن فهذه آلة
called the ToucHB Quik.
تدعى ToucHB Quik.
What it does
ما تقوم به
is it measures my hemoglobin, oxygen and pulse rate.
هو أنها تقيس الهيموغلوبين والأوكسجين وسرعة النبض.
I put it on my finger, switch it on,
أضعه على اصبعي، وأشغله،
and in about 20 seconds
وفي غضون حوالي 20 ثانية
it'll give me, on the little screen here,
ستعطيني، على الشاشة الصغيرة هنا،
a value of hemoglobin,
قيمة للهيموغلوبين،
oxygen saturation and heart rate.
للأوكسجين ومعدل ضربات القلب.
This will help ASHA workers
هذا سيساعد عمال الآشا
diagnose anemia at the point of care.
لتشخيص فقر الدم في نقطة الرعاية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I'll explain a little bit about how it works.
سأشرح قليلا عن كيفية عمله.
You might have seen a little light inside of it.
قد تكونون قد رأيتم ضوء خافتا بداخله.
In fact, there are three lights in there, three wavelengths of light.
في الواقع، هناك ثلاثة أضواء هناك، ثلاث أطوال موجية للضوء
And we essentially pass light
ونقوم أساسا بتمرير الضوء
right through the tissue,
من خلال النسيج،
and from understanding how much of it is transmitted,
ومن خلال فهم مقدار ما يتم تمريره،
how much of it is scattered and how much of it is absorbed,
مقدار ما يتم بعثرته ومقدار ما يتم امتصاصه،
we can figure out
يمكننا معرفة
how much hemoglobin is there in the blood.
مقدار الهيموغلوبين الموجود في الدم.
And this is something which is based on a principle
وهذا شيء يعتمد على مبدأ
called photoplethysmography.
يدعى تخطيط التحجم الضوئي.
We are actually really very excited
نحن فعلا متحمسون للغاية
about what else non-invasive techniques like this
حول الأمور الأخرى التي يمكن لتكنولوجيا غير جراحية مثل هذه
will be able to crack in the future.
أن تكون قادرة على حلها في المستقبل.
One of the things which my intern here, Pratesh, built
أحد الأشياء التي بناها متدربي هنا، براتيش،
is a mobile application,
هو تطبيق محمول،
which can now send all this data anywhere it wants to go.
والذي يمكن أن يرسل كل هذه البيانات إلى أي مكان تريد الذهاب إليه.
There's a bunch of very exciting stuff which we are doing.
هناك باقة من الأشياء المثيرة للحماس نقوم بها.
I would love to tell you a little bit more about it.
أرغب في إخباركم القليل بخصوصها.
But fundamentally,
لكن أساسا،
what I believe is that the map behind of me
ما أؤمن به هو أن الخريطة ورائي
is called basically the map of anemia.
تدعى أساسا خريطة فقر الدم.
It's the death rates caused by anemia globally.
إنها معدلات الوفايات بفقر الدم على الصعيد العالمي.
You'll notice, of course,
ستلاحظون، بالطبع،
that there are hot spots --
أنه هناك نقاط ساخنة --
South Asia, Africa.
جنوب آسيا، أفريقيا.
My business plan is very simple.
و خطة عملي بسيطة للغاية.
I'm just going to sell these to every clinic in the world.
سأقوم فقط ببيع هذه لكل عيادة في العالم.
That's a simple bottom-line business plan.
تلك خطة عمل أرباح صافية.
And by the time I'm done, in 2020,
وبمجرد انتهائي، سنة 2020،
when the WHO publishes the data again,
حين تنشر منظمة الصحة العالمية البيانات مجددا،
this is going to be the map of anemia.
هذا ما ستبدو عليه خريطة فقر الدم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.